hello welcome to today's solution
raising today we are tackling a more
complex topic comfortable topic of
prisons and I honestly don't know what
we are gonna come up with this topic was
chosen before the murder of George Floyd
so I want to reiterate that we're
probably going to be talking about race
because I can't imagine getting through
talking about prisons without I think
you have done it on service but a
solution are we seen we spend an hour
talking about that topic we spend 15
minutes talking about what it currently
looks like what we like what we don't
like about it what's working what's not
15 minutes talking about our beautiful
version of a future that we would love
to see happen and they don't need to
match and then we spend half an hour
talking about what we could do with
10,000 people and $100,000 and prisons
is a hard one to tackle with that but
I'm interested to see what we could come
up with that moves that forward in any
way and it what it is today so if anyone
would like to start sharing what how
they see the prison system right now and
I can always start future I mean I can
always start to but I said pretty much
always do so I'm and I'm waiting for
somebody else to jump in for a change
all right I will I could quit and then
okay so prisons oh my goodness but just
because I was actually prepared to talk
about racism and I was also like there
is a disproportionate amount of a lot of
people in prison there's a
disproportionate amount of black people
in the state's disproportional amount of
First Nations in Canada and I'm sure in
the states as well and there's also a
lot of people with neurodiversity
a lot of people with mental illness a
lot of people with physical disabilities
in prison per the population basically
it is the position of prison is to keep
people away from society and there's a
good part of that I don't want murderers
and rapists running around amongst us
and there's also now we don't need to
think about them and they're away and
who we put in that category right but
it's smoking a joint you got you there
in some places and the level of
criminality as well as our we are our
criminals in prison so they can be
punished or they therefore reform
because I don't think we can do both and
I think we concentrate on punishment
there's of course the whole funnel
leading into the prison system and the
funnel leading out of the prison system
who gets there is all of the stuff right
the racism and disability and and
classism for sure and then when you get
out have any criminal records like you
already had a hard time now you're in
prison and now you have a criminal
record now you can't vote and have a say
in anything and so although prison is
kind of what we're focusing this on I
don't think we can talk about it without
the funnel going in and the funnel you
know as well and so that is a bit of
what I want to share on prisons is of
course the criminal justice system whole
legal like it pertains to everything but
who else would like to share adequate
I've got a few things actually which
occurred to me while you were talking
so yeah the notion of the record is
really is a really important thing right
it's such a it's such a handicap for the
rest of your life once you're stamped as
a criminal of any kind and certain types
of criminal in particular and so it it
almost removes any possibility of
redemption and rehabilitation and and
turning your life around kind of thing
right so there that that's that's
something and what it's for is also a
really interesting question is it to
punish people like take their freedom
away from them and lock them up as a
form of punishment for their wrongdoing
or is it to keep dangerous people away
from society at large right now I mean
it's it's a little bit of both the
punishment thing yeah I guess I mean
depriving someone of their liberty is a
pretty serious punishment and it seems
to me ought to be reserved for pretty
serious crimes and the type of poems
where you can't have that person
wandering around inside you know it
seems to me the punishment fitting the
crime so if you steal something from
someone then you go and do a few day's
work for them in order to repay the debt
and also you now form a relationship
within this possibility of forgiveness
and and what's it calls earn as a
process as a name for this process
I can't think of it'll come to me at
some point so yeah that's another thing
and my final point is
I'm Jude Jubilee alluded to this but I
just want to expand on it a little bit
is you know when you really put someone
in prison you can kind of forget well
they're a bad person we put them in
prison they've done their time they come
out blah blah blah blah blah but the
social circumstances which will have led
them to some degree or another you can
argue about to what degree but to some
degree or other to commit those crimes
in the first place I mean it seems to be
almost universal that people who abuse
their children were themselves abused as
children right and so you know things
like this is it is it actually right at
all to consider the person perpetrating
the crime as a criminal when so often
actually they are victims just
recreating the cycle you know what I
mean and and so yeah I I will get onto
this later on but it seems to me that
the emphasis is entirely in the wrong
place you know that you put all of the
blame on the person who committed the
act and none of the blame it's all on
the society that that produced that
person right that's that's it that's my
point
I guess I'll go um I have to agree with
most of what both of you have said and I
also like to add that for me I believe
that our education system also adds to
this because you're you start to be
graded or either you're good or you're
bad at a very young age and we start to
have a complex about that as it you know
you internalize it and you think you are
bad and then you start to feel like oh I
don't fit in in this a group or the rich
people or the sporty people or whatever
so then you kind of start associating
yourself with the bad people or whatever
which often can be taken and you can be
taken advantage of because you're still
you young you still are impressionable
but you have these powerful people that
maybe have their own records that will
try to use you to meet their needs in a
way because they think you're young
you'll you know go to juvie you'll get
out you'll be fine but in reality it's
just at the beginning of that whole
system and and you can't it's very very
difficult to get out of it I mean almost
impossible I agree with so much that you
guys have already said and I'd love to
hear what dr. Noah has to say
I don't think I have anything to add yet
but when I do I'll say thanks Joshua I
well Eric was talking I definitely had a
few other things come up one of which is
the privatization of prisons Sheridan
actually suggested on the posting game
be that that was kind of like that we
could maybe have would I like an
integral prison right and although part
of my brain started running and I was
like oh and not be awesome right got
organic Gardens and the prisoner the
prison has a monopoly over your life and
you don't get to choose which prison you
go to and therefore even if you made one
beautiful you're not actually solving it
because the person doesn't get to choose
right there isn't competition in prisons
because it's the judges who decide where
you go and that is is that there's
there's supreme power that isn't checked
the prison guards the prison what is the
person in charge of the prison the
prison I can't remember what the name is
and the judges and how much morning
hey it's funny I didn't hear you because
you're a mute but I thought it's very
bitter in it as well as the fact that no
matter how perfect your criminal justice
system is there's always going to be
innocent people in prison and so we need
to treat our prison population as
they're innocent like duty and so if
we're punishing them right we know that
somewhat amongst them is innocent we
can't really have a prison system where
absolutely there's nobody in it and like
if we have one at all it isn't
there's no innocent people in it and
guilty people running around free also
right yeah yes absolutely and then the
media and bias like we're seeing even we
talk about education that the prison
there
funnel into the prison system that our
prison that our cops are racist and
ableist and classist and everything else
it comes from a lot of what the media
that they watch we see right now there's
a lot of hate crime towards Asians and
there's a lot of hate crime even towards
nurses and doctors and that's three
months right of dealing with a crisis
that you feel they're somehow
responsible for doing that for decades
for centuries like we can't just
did overnight and yet the media plays
into it the unconscious bias plays into
it when you see someone perpetrate a
crime against you and then you start
saying that people like that are in that
category and therefore all those people
are that makes somewhat sense when it's
your own your own world right you're
Olivia you're in a tribe you next to
another tribe those members there's an
evolutionary reason we have that and at
the same time our media feeds that and
so seeing even if you never encounter
let's say a black person in real life
who's gonna rob you you encounter them
time and time and time again on the
media doing that and so you start to
form these subconscious bias that those
people are bad and those people are the
problem even if you've never encountered
one and so there's this subconscious
bias that comes in that we had that
again we have to kind of correct
everything all at once it's not just the
prison system right it's the education
it's the media it's all of it's the
political system it's how do we hold
police accountable but I don't want to
get too broad for it but I did want to
just say that that was one of the things
that came up I just wanted to quickly
add I completely agree with it being I
do not believe that prison system should
be for profit in any way I just it's
sickening I feel the same about health
care but I'm much more concerned about
the prison system because they can keep
you trapped in this system any little
thing you do wrong there and they're
making all this money off you and we're
paying for that a couple of judges who
have been found guilty of taking
backhanders from prison companies in
order to send kids to jail who really
shouldn't agree had tiny nothing
offenses you know what I mean and
they've ended up spending years there
and the prison companies made millions
out there yeah I know but this is
exactly what happens when you start
swing center by sending people to jail
right inevitable are we mainly talking
about the u.s. here no prison system in
Canada though I don't I don't you think
clients of prisons exist in many other
places in the world I mean they probably
do in stuff but yeah I mean I don't know
that he but I it's not a widespread
thing certainly not in the UK we don't
have prisons
although that said that said young
offenders institutions and detentions
and things like that not not secure you
know not not category one two or three
prisons but anything below that I
believe can be private public
partnerships kind of thing so whenever
you when you whenever you have an organ
of government that's privatized it
really gets this inertia to its where
like it's now there's people who's now
there's a big corporation whose
existence depends on this thing
continuing to happen and in fact depends
on this thing growing so like it just
the more government privatizes its
functions the more immobile it becomes
and they're less flexible it becomes
so that's something we need to think
about like what is going to happen to
the private prison system are they gonna
it's so hard to bankrupt a large
business like that they have so much
power for lobbying and for everything
like if we're not gonna if we if we do
want to take them down that's extremely
difficult if we don't want to take them
down then we need to figure out some
other way that some other kind of
business that they can convert into I
personally fully okay with them going
bankrupt I know like the oil and gas
industry I'm not unlike those are people
who don't mean my country right who
don't have an education they make
hundreds of thousands or a hundred
thousand dollars a year there is nowhere
else for them to transition into and I
feel really badly for them I feel zero
like oh no the shareholders are the
prisoner funny like Naaman and I realize
that but like no shareholder ever should
make a penny off of somebody else being
in prison there should be no
shareholders that's a ridiculous system
yeah I'm not saying that I would don't
want them to go bankrupt
of course they do but even even without
even without private prisons there is
still incentive in the system to
incarcerate people right because you
have the whole time taking the UK as an
example right you have the home office
which gets however many hundreds of
millions of pounds a year it gets from
the from the chart from the Treasury in
order to finance it's under there now if
it starts so reduce the prison
population well now is going to get a
smaller budget right in the civil
servants in the minister won't have that
you know they
they want a bigger budget every year
they growing so you know even even when
there is not profit to be made from its
incentives exist to expand the prison
service incarcerate more people so that
the Minister can say look we're being
tough on crime all that kind of bollocks
you know what I mean it's interesting
the difference between the education
system but it comes with a lot of those
things but like a teacher a
superintendent doesn't go around talking
about birth control or not birth control
right like they don't increase their
it's just however much the population
had a baby that's what they kind of have
to deal with when they turn five that's
what any people are in the education
system and yet of course they're still
problems of classroom sizes and all the
other stuff that comes with budgets but
if we did judge jails based on what
they're actually there to do
theoretically
right which is through this ism I can't
say the word how many criminals recommit
crimes when they get out and that was
what you actually got your budget on you
know what I mean like if you're a
shareholder you get it you get a bonus
based on how hard are you doing your job
sense of structure where you incentivize
a low recidivism rate right you had a
clear problem if you manager a low
recidivism rate then the prisons are not
going to want people to be incarcerated
again once they get out even if they
commit crimes well but they could but
the hopefully the prison system is a
separate entity from the criminal
justice system which actually puts
people in the prisons in the first place
right and so the prison actually has
nothing to do with who gets sent back to
prison or not but if they do get sent
back to a prison any prison there and it
tracks back to the first prison they
were in right are this person has
recommitted a time therefore you get a
cut in your future payment or a penalty
or you don't get your bonus or whatever
it might be and if you're I'm absolutely
certain there would be incentives that
would break it that's because there is
there are ways but I do like that I do
like that oh is that someone graduates
from your prison system and then ends up
back up in the prison system
on you and what what percentage does
this prism have a recidivism versus this
one versus this one and looking at those
type of information but the issue is
just do we have butts in the seat
because we get X amount per prisoner and
yeah you want it and then judges are on
the board and like shareholders of those
things and so the more prisoners they
send to those prisons the more money
they get that is just a clear corrupt
violation and I just started to realize
it sorry which means you are they
incentivized to maintain ten conditions
in the prison which encouraged people to
commit more crimes when they get out the
other side you don't make them incapable
of living any kind of life other than a
life of crime when they get out so that
they recommit offenses so they come back
to jail so that you get future profits
you know I mean there's two things which
occur to me which I think lead us nicely
into the next section if I may so first
thing is if prisons were not based
primarily around taking your freedom
away but were based primarily around
retraining you so that you know
retraining you and and dealing with your
shifts so such that you might be a
constructive member of the society how
about if you weren't locked up right so
you turn up in the morning you go home
in the evening fails to do that then you
can't then you get locked up right there
you get arrest and you get locked up but
give prisoners the opportunity to
actually turn up and do a day of
whatever the training is and it's
assuming it's meaningful and my second
point and this this is the big one
really is to reclassify not just in name
but in the way that we think about it
and the way that we interact with it we
designate the criminal justice system as
the conflict resolution or this conflict
little dispute resolution service or
something like that right
in recognition of the fact that even
good people actually in good faith come
into conflict from time to time right
and and you know having mechanisms in
the in the society at every level to
deal with this right you know you know
within the family unit and you know
training exists at school and outside of
school and there's Public Information
films and you know it's part of the
public literature and the national
discourse in the news and
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah how to how to
deal with conflict at the family level
at the neighborhood level at the
community level at the citywide level do
you know what I mean and and really have
that as a main focus of what we like
woven right into the fabric of what we
do as a society because as we've talked
about before Jubilee I don't know if
you've been present for these shows
before conflict should actually be
celebrated right conflict the clash of
difference is an opportunity for new
understanding and new learning to take
place right friction creates forward
motion when the rubber hits the road
it's the friction which creates forward
motion right so it's a question of
taking their energy and harnessing it in
a constructive manner rather than it
have it all burn off as heat and
argument and that kind of thing right so
yeah I it seems especially with what's
been going on in the game bSpace
recently the the ability to turn you
know pointless bickering type arguments
into constructive
not debate I hate the word debate
because debate is is the same thing
arguing over a single property but you
know a constructive generation of of new
ideas something like that there we go
that's that's that's my lead-in to
Section C so this section because Joshua
hasn't participated yet no solution AZ
and as we talk about our beautiful
version of the future they don't need to
match so if someone else says something
you're like no I don't like that that's
not my beautiful future that's okay it's
like your version of what that what that
looks like
um this is a weird one for me because
this this area of society it doesn't
exist in my vision of the future like
that we have a place we put people we
don't want to deal with I do think
there's probably a very tiny subsection
of our population that no matter how
great their nutrition and parenting and
everything as might be people who we're
still murderers so rapists still need to
be not in society those will be way less
than what they are now and they still
need to have dignity they still might be
innocent they still might be like they
still have to have a quality of life
that they would want to participate in I
think having if there are prisons having
them run by the prisoners without it
being Anarchy having them look at the
budget what do we want to eat right like
if we have three dollars per mouth to
feed per meal how much can we garden and
do things that add to that right how can
we make sure everyone has has that have
them actually work together deal with
conflict to deal with how do we make
these decisions made and looking I mean
looking at when you're in a prison
system that you basically need to join a
gang and like looking at like okay well
what is the how can we bring in actual
conflict resolution and governance that
they want to be part of and have it be
it is something that they can keep
reiterating have it be iterative so it
can it can grow and they can they can
learn from it because then our prison
coming out of the prison system they'd
be better than the rest of us you don't
like how often do I get the
participation of how I've liked coming
together with a group of people in the
society when are we gonna eat how are we
going to bring that cost down how are we
going to to do that how are we going to
one of the other things that kind of
belongs in the last section when Eric
was talking was that a lot of our
criminal justice system is dealing with
human nature
in its natural state like that when
we're under stress we go through fight
flight or freeze flight is hit and run
right fight is like any kind of violence
that comes out of it and it's like is
that right do I want to just give
everyone a pass no but I do want to own
that that's your nervous system if you
don't have any option but to fight we
need to give you another option we need
to give you other avenues so that that
moment's a decision grows and you have
other things to do I know mine is
freebies and shut down I don't have a
choice in that luckily it's not illegal
like luckily it's not illegal to shut
down so it's like if I just don't
respond I'm not going to jail for it
probably unless I'm with a cop they
really need me to respond in the way
they want but I have other privileges
safe from that so yes my version of a
beautiful future is there are no prisons
and we deal with the in and the out in a
much more beautiful way that there we
don't have police officers we have
conflict resolution officers depending
on what the crisis is how do we respond
to it and what does that look like and I
think it is something we do from that
from the ground up and I don't know
exactly what that looks like but I think
we have I think a decent starting point
actually is is already in existence I
mean the notion of common law if it here
- right I mean I I know it's been
captured in many ways by politics and
money I get that but but the notion
itself of you know trial in a place
where all arguments are heard and a
decision is made by a jury of your peers
right and a punishment is decided on by
a experienced judge member of the
community whatever you know is that that
model something along those lines seems
to me to be very fair because you know
you then have a record of the kind of
thing that has gone before so what does
the size society deem in general to be
an appropriate punishment or an
appropriate form of retribution or
penance or whatever for this for this
particular transgression but it's
updatable right as time goes on and the
individual circumstances of this
particular situation are heard by actual
people who make a decision based on that
right and and and sentencing also should
you know can involve and involve the
jury you know conversation with the
judge so you
this-this-this kind of model again with
widespread participate I'm not seeing
everyone sitting on juries every day of
their lives right but but jury service
is a regular feature of daily life right
that it is a privilege to engage in the
process of keeping a society running
smoothly and healthy and keeping
relations constructive between people by
participating in the fair process of
conflict resolution right and by
participating in it you will understand
yourself when you arrive in conflict you
know how am I I better deal with this so
that I turned up in front of the
jury so we could spend less time in jury
that would actually a really good metric
I want to give Josh one Shilo a chance
to share their vision of a future so I
yeah I really liked the conflict
prioritizing conflict resolution and
restorative justice over a punitive
justice Stoller's justice thank you
that's the term that was looking cool
thank you yeah if if there is a if
there's someone who's just so some so
like dysfunctional and that they that
their community can't handle them then
maybe some kind of state institution
would be a good idea now I don't think
that the right thing for that state
institution to do would be to punish
this person I think it would be to
rehabilitate them and right now we don't
have the therapeutic technologies to
rehabilitate everybody who's capable of
ribbing rehabilitated we can basically
only do the easiest cases but if we um
if we just like get much better at that
make better technologies etc we'll be
able to rehabilitate a much larger
amount of people and the better we get
the more people we can rehabilitate like
I don't think it's like a rehabilitated
tubule or not I think it's about how
difficult it is to rehabilitate this
person and how much time and energy it
will take like maybe there's somebody
who's so difficult to rehabilitate that
you need a team of 20 um 20
psychologists working all the time to
figure out how to do it but even even if
that was necessary for some people I
think it's a
it should be done unless the society
just does not have the resources to do
it so that's the other case what if the
society just simply doesn't have the
resources to rehabilitate some people
and they also can't be led out into the
general Society for those people if we
really can't rehabilitate them and what
Australia that's the case there no no no
I was just saying that's what Australia
was for that's exactly what we used to
do was dump all of those people in
Australia I think I would actually I'm
very cautious about this because I don't
I don't wouldn't trust the the US for
example I don't I'm against the death
penalty in the US just simply because I
don't trust the government to administer
it properly are there's too many
innocent people who get in trouble etc
but if I actually trusted the government
then I would think that the death
penalty is a good idea for people who
can't be who the society does not have
the means to rehabilitate and also you
don't want in the general sphere because
otherwise you're just keeping them
around and you you don't have the means
to help him and you can't let them out
so what's the point
a secure island somewhere would be a bit
maybe but yeah maybe if you collect
Rissa tea and internet and TV and blah
blah blah blah blah yeah they could
still as Jubilee said before have some
sort of quality of life some sort of
dignity some sort of self-determination
but they're not a threat to anyone else
right there in the middle of the ocean
thousands of miles away from anyone else
can't do any harm right okay yeah that
work says hey we don't need to agree on
it because I don't agree on on the death
penalty but I love how even though that
little piece yeah that could work I love
it um Shilo do you have anything you
would like to add to the session yeah um
like like you Jubilee I feel like there
is we need to there's systemic change
that has to happen because it's all
driven by money one way or another
either we have enough finances or
to make money off people that is the
only measurement that we measure our
countries our communities with is that
they are financially wealthy or not
that's like our one measurement so I
really believe we need a universal
humanitarian well system that actually
gives people value on all these
different levels including our
communities and I really believe that
beginning the process in your community
where you okay this is a very personal
thing for me I it's really hard to say
but I'm gonna say it I committed a crime
when I was young teenager and it was
kind of like I was saying earlier like
you get judged for so long as you're
growing up through your community your
school and I felt like I really needed
to like make my presence known in the
bad group because I wasn't fitting into
the good group let's say and so I went
and decided to steal some alcohol
because you know it's cool to have
alcohol with your friends when you're a
teenager so I went to like well I was
homeless so I stayed with people but I
went to their neighbor's house and stole
some booze with some friends and then
stashed it and then the next day we went
to get it and the cops caught us and you
know they played good kept bad cop there
at each of us they're like they said it
was you they said it was you so we all
admitted that yeah we sold it from this
house well I ended up getting a felony
conviction for that stealing alcohol as
a teenager before I could even drive so
I had a felony on my record mm-hmm and
I'm white I'm you know white middle
class let's say I tried to ignore the
fact that I yes I went through juvie
all this I didn't really try to
acknowledge the fact I couldn't vote
because I didn't really understand the
power of a vote at the time when I was a
teenager so what's my point here my
point is I feel like I was able to just
hide that from society and from myself I
never processed it I felt like a really
bad person I knew the people that I
stole from I felt really guilty but I
never had to confront them like there
was a woman a grandmother in the house I
didn't know she was in the house during
the time I just went in the garage let's
say and stole beer whatever out of the
fridge in the garage but she was
terrified and I feel like a better
solution would have been me having to
confront her come to her and say for one
thing I did not mean to terrify you I
was just trying to be cool with some
idiots at school and I was so wrong and
if I could have met her face to face
done work for her right you know
provided some sort of support for her
she was needy she was an elderly woman
stuck in a home I could have done
something to help her and make a real
connection have a real relationship with
someone this is all about that's exactly
what it's all about it gives her a
chance to give you and you a chance to
be forgiven and you know the slates have
been wiped clean I actually wipe the
slate clean you know whereas you are
obviously still suffering from the
memory of it right you felt shame your
whole life as a well you know you that
that burden could have been lifted from
you I mean I don't you most likely she
probably remember it right most likely
but you know who knows maybe she's maybe
you know she was terrified at the time
maybe she is long term so who knows who
knows but yeah it can all be gone it can
all go away that's exactly what
restorative justice is all about and I
think you can start really young cuz we
make mistakes I mean because we don't
know yet when we're young we make
mistakes because we don't know what the
result is that's why we're making
mistakes and you can start very young
and help people make correct decisions
and there's we don't need this prison
system and and maybe like you're all
saying there is a smaller system but
maybe we can still participate as a
community and volunteer to be a part of
this small system that needs
to help rehabilitate people that seem to
be unrevealed we can't do that for and
so I don't know there's just so much
wealth in our interconnectivity and
helping one another I feel like that is
a place that we could really grow and
build that I'm sorry I probably didn't
need to go so personal but it does still
affect me and I'm sure that does all
these people that are dealing with it
when I think it was a very powerful
story to sure to share Shiloh I think it
was perfect
um I think we can have a whole
conversation on time so we should have
been arrested and weren't or you know
any vice versa and that whole like I
know my experiences are I'm like I would
have been in prison several times if I
didn't have my white sweet girl you know
I couldn't do anything wrong privileged
literate like constantly I'm like you
don't even know you should probably be
following me around the grocery store
and not that other person in my in my
times of youth and that those are
important conversations like that I have
a heart for people who have a criminal
drug to have a criminal record because I
know I could have one but then other
people who that happens to it's like
they somehow feel that that kind of
privilege gives them permission that no
I did well I didn't get arrested for it
right so you must have been even worse
you must have done even worse things if
you not only did them but got arrested
and it's like right no cuz the cops find
your smoking pot and you know bring it
home to your parents and still I do you
steal and it's like oh it's the one time
one time thing it's you transition into
the next part which is the the solutions
what we could actually do to improve our
prison system with 10,000 people and
$100,000 whether that is concentrating
again on like Canada of the UK the
United States or globally depends on the
10,000 and I did not have an idea for
this but during the conversation with
Shila just shared I actually have a idea
but I want to see if anyone else has an
idea
I mean uncle account under the current
system a victim is required right there
needs to be someone who has been harmed
in some way too so I mean it seems to me
that a community level one could figure
out something along the lines of rather
than going to the police and reporting
this as a crime can we sit around a
table and hash it out between us and you
know what I mean something like that
so that that guy I mean that doesn't
require really any money it's really
requires effort it requires effort is
what it requires and I think it requires
a neutral space in your community to be
able to do that which most communities
in America really don't have that mutual
space where people can come together one
of the things I thought about when Shilo
it was was sharing her story was what
would be really powerful is getting I
don't need to be 10,000 honestly a
hundred a thousand people together out
of any there's a crime right you stole
domestic violence whatever the crime is
getting people who've committed that
crime who went to prison for that crime
together to kompis solutions not for the
prison but for right like I was involved
in domestic violence what would that
have looked like where no one went to
prison right what would it look like to
deal with that in a family unit without
ignoring it but actually doing and
having the people who actually been in
that moment been in that fight flight or
freeze and chosen fight right what does
that look like to de-escalate what does
it look like to give people a solution
that isn't prison for that and same as
stealing same with any of it right like
why are you stealing why are you doing
that and then looking at what is
something that could be in place to
bring that crime level down right have a
have mediation have conflict resolution
that doesn't go through the court system
but has an option because the issues
also you need both the victim and the
perpetrator or whatever wording is to
agree right and restorative
it's like if one person wants to go
regular dress and what a computed
injustice and the other person wants
restorative who wins right and it's like
well maybe the victim I don't know who
gets to choose right that was part of
what I wanted to put in the last section
but maybe this is um and I have ideas
because when we say a jury of your peers
you actually get to choose who those
peers are so you know anything like I
don't know who my peers would be but I
would know if they're not on the jury
right if I'm a black man and the entire
jury looks like white people well no I
actually wanted a jury of black people
if I can voice that I should be given it
because of a if the jury of black people
wouldn't find me guilty you don't like
that that seems that is the jury of your
peers and that's honestly what white
people get anyway like that level of oh
you look like my cousin and you look
like my brother I'll give you a little
more leeway and so to have a jury of
your actual peers is and then oh like
it's like well I'm a murderer I want to
do a bunch of murderers I don't know how
far it goes but that eats just
articulated and then to be in the court
system what is and isn't considered
acceptable a jury of your peers I really
like that idea of the option to choose
if you want to go restorative justice or
punitive justice and and you as the
person that committed the crime get to
kind of choose that and then following
that with you know a metric system that
follows them through their life to help
them not recommit finding ways I feel
like part of this humanitarian system I
think of is our interconnectedness and
the ability for people that commit
crimes to go into their community and
ask for help and ask like I'm struggling
I don't have a job you know whatever the
reason they're different things are and
find different maybe mentors in their
community to help them step up to the
next level so that we're always we
realize we're always learning we're
always improving and giving those people
the opportunity to do that and with a
hand like
helping them it's so hard on your own to
figure out just morale he's clean
especially when your prefrontal cortex
isn't fully developed which is right
they crowed the adults you get to vote
as a teen your prefrontal cortex is
until you're what 23 24 and so heaven
for bit and then like 15 6 general
commits a crime we try them as an adult
that's not the right direction like
that's not it
I know I did decisions at 15 or 16 I was
a very smart 15 or 16 year old and I
still did things that I'm like what were
you thinking and like you were saying
about neurodiversity or mental illness I
mean we're holding people trapped in
hell basically who just just never had
an opportunity I totally I just can't
believe what we do to people I don't
know how to change like if we have this
$100,000 or whatever I mean it just
seems like such a huge thing to change
but we have to you just here's the point
it's like it feels like the only way we
could possibly tackle prisons is
systemically and systemic change is hard
and difficult and so it's almost like
throw up your hands there's no point
that's why we're having the solution
raising is there's always something that
can be done right now that it's absolute
like I have a ton of ideas sparking for
this for this space like we could
because judges are any time they make a
verdict any time they it's on public
record well we could have a database of
that we could see what cops sent who to
prison what judges sent who to prison we
can see the blatant racism when it
happens and because it's public we don't
need their permission that you know what
I mean if we have enough other people
when I have an interaction with a cop I
just plug it right did they pull me over
yes no didn't I get a ticket yes no was
I speeding
yes I don't know yes no right like what
was actually there you need more people
than like if we need more data so the
more people are putting doubt in the
system the better it is but to be able
to showcase those kind of things to be
able to there was a anytime anyone else
wants to chime in to take off from you
cuz I'll just run through
there was a what is it called The Good
Wife and there's a spin-off called The
Good Life or good law or something and
one of the people in it I don't remember
which which where there's a spin-off or
not but he brought an app he was in
prison he wrote an app that was helping
prisoners navigate the legal system from
within the prison so when when the
prison does something wrong to you and
you need to request tampons when you
need to like this is the this is the
process you go through and it helps you
go through the process you don't need to
get outside counsel this app is kind of
your outside counsel and the lawyers
bought it and put it on and because they
didn't want their jobs we take it over
so they bought it made it not exist and
what I understand something like that
this is a fictional it's actually very
powerful to be able to help to be able
to bring prisoners together after they
get out to start their own worker
cooperatives so it doesn't matter if you
have a criminal background that we know
because no one asks an entrepreneur
right if you hire a plumber you don't
ask them for their criminal record check
it's the you know like they can they can
find jobs and they can't get hired by
someone else who isn't gonna take on
that liability of hiring someone with a
criminal record whereas there's other
entrepreneurial groups that do take that
on that's like their whole mission but
then you have to be accepted for that
group if there was always a way to start
a worker cooperative what can you learn
in prison and when you get out you can
be part of this Union
roughy figuring out how to bring people
together who are directly impacted the
families of the people in prison how do
we witness what they're eating what
their punishments are how long they've
been in solitary confinement that you
know I mean there's people on me even if
they don't have the privilege of the
internet there's people on the outside
who are their loved ones who can you can
feed that back into the system so that
we can witness it and do something
because you know Todd eating like crap
all day every day is is like his
family's problem but all of you doing it
is like our problem and when we see it
on mass scale and see what's happening
but they're not having heat they're not
letting let out drink Obed they're not
you know they're in their cells 24 3
hours a day whatever it happens to be
that were able to just witness it and
hopefully come up with things from the
bottom up that hold the top down powers
accountable
everybody else's on me yeah okay I don't
have solutions but I did just two other
things I want to bring up one is that I
don't know about other countries but in
the u.s. about half of the people in in
jails are haven't even been tried yet
they're awaiting trial and they can't
afford bail yeah so just fixing the
justice system won't fix the prison
system there's different the other thing
I want to point out is that another
incentive for imprisoning people is that
you get cheap labor you don't need to
pay prisoners minimum wage so a lot of
stuff is made by prisoners at tracking
what the is made by prisoners like
my lingeries me buy them or something
right and how much did they get paid per
hour because there's learning a skill
and then there's just slave labor and
it's pretty clear which ones which
and so Italy don't II met their fire
fighting for a dollar a day know if
they're learning how to fire fight and
they can do it on the other end they're
volunteering to do they're volunteering
to do that to feel like they're
contributing that's a very different
route than like oh you get it all or a
day so you can you know buy things from
the canteen um and just making sure
everyone in person has a buddy right not
a like a pen pal someone who like okay
well even if you don't have a witness on
the outside I will be your witness check
and you pass if there's people on the
outside witnessing and prisoners sign up
for that and you don't check in for a
week and we throw up the red alert
they're in or Dineen like there's
there's ways we can we can have power
without remember what y'all just said
that I wanted to everyone just as body
system that's a brilliant idea
where every prisoner has somebody on the
outside that they communicate with
regularly and if the person on the
outside doesn't hear from them or ever
they can raise an alarm of some kind wow
that's a really really good idea and
they confide in them and the letters
don't get read by the prison something
like that is a really good idea that's
why it was there people in prison who
haven't been tried tracking that right
how long is this person been in well
look if you were white you could have
the $10,000 bail having bail bonds that
aren't bail bonds right they were like
look we can see we can see you're an
upstanding member of society
we will front you the money right like
like this isn't the bail bonds having
alternative solutions to this is
ridiculous that you're sitting in prison
and that you are then a you're earning
money for the prison instead of being
able to provide for your family when
you're probably not even guilty and it's
poverty that's keeping you they're not
your crime and even if it was how do we
you know do everything else we've talked
about that just owning that those things
exist and then how do we track them
who's in prison and how long have they
been there this is not a speedy justice
system even if they committed the crime
how bad is it on the outside right if
they were murdering raping yeah I kind
of want them locked up right but like if
they're they smoked a joint
oh no heaven forbid they do that well
they wait I wait trial right like what
is the what is the level of I don't care
because of course race honey classism
come into it can you before is there's
so many different solutions like and it
seems like you need to do all of them
they're all connected like maybe
something to do with the $10,000 is set
up a foundation that that that gives
grants to people who are trying to fix
this prison system yeah I like that
I also think that we could help the
justice system reduce its caseload if we
were doing community justice at the
lowest end maybe that could help reduce
the amount of people that need to be
seen in courts therefore helping that
yeah I don't know I think I feel like if
we can come together better as a society
and support one another and spend it
just competing with each other then we
have this opportunity to really change
you realize that our value is connected
with one another's value in our
community and therefore trying to help
people improve giving them opportunities
yeah having a I'm having a better
alternative
the system is definitely very helpful
towards dismantling the prison system
but it's not it's not the whole story
because let's say a community tries to
have a better alternative they're trying
to do community justice but there's cops
still patrolling still arresting people
still incarcerating people and the cops
don't give a about their their
community justice the cops just want to
fill their quotas or whatever you need
to have a better alternative but you
also need to try to change that it on
defund the police at like proportionally
to making the better alternative that
your alternative oh that's replace the
police
I completely agree and I feel like
having a humanitarian well system we
also I mean the police are actually
using that as well and therefore there's
a record of the interactions and they're
more accountable then because our our
interactions with the police or more at
a community equal face-to-face level so
we're getting to know them better
they're seeing our improvements we're
seeing where they're acting and act
you're incorrectly their abuse I just
feel like having our metrics on it would
be help a different type of metrics like
yeah not just the camera that they can
turn on or off the origin of policing in
the I mean again it's not like this
anymore but the origin of policing in UK
it was by consent right you know people
from the community volunteered to you
know be of service to those that needed
help kind of thing and it was and it was
all all originated in and was done with
the consent of the community and the
people and again this feels like it's an
ancient notion but it seems to be one
worth resurrecting and see if it can be
invigorated I feel like this is maybe
not the place when 10 minutes left but
like what I'm when I'm struggling with
leadership in the game be space and that
the game be people aren't like policing
themselves right like they're not
moderating themselves they need someone
else
and there's a truth to that and there's
also like there's a truth to that in
this conversation of like restorative
justice is the community taking care of
in a very beautiful way at the same time
there's a community justice that is not
like that which is you know like lynch
mobs and and that level of life right so
so how do you make sure there is that
where we're not just kicking people out
to kick them out and we're not like how
do we not leave it up to a central
authority to do restored to do justice
because when it's at a central authority
it's really easy to put everything on
them right you're not you're not
arrested enough of the criminals and at
the same time you're arresting too many
right because those are for two
different people so it's like they can't
make everyone happy whereas together
it's like what is the crime rate what
crimes are actually crimes and can we
bring those down why are people stealing
why are people in so much conflict that
they feel they need to commit violence
how do we keep bringing that down and
although you're right we need all of
these things in place that we talked
about any single one of them would be
powerful and what's even more powerful
is that ten thousand people know they
can get together to create them they do
create all of them not just one of them
and so if we had a way to track the
judges and track the the police officers
to know if they're being races and a way
to buddy up with the prison's the people
in prison to watch and witness and help
them improve life while they're in there
and a way to help them have jobs and
vote and have a real decent life on the
way out all of that can take place and
and I want to help that even though I'm
not involved in that criminal justice
system right I mean I don't I'm not a
prisoner I've never had any of my loved
ones be a prisoner and at the same time
even without anyone's involvement from
the outside they could do it themselves
right just people who've been through
the prison system could create something
to witness done better they don't need
an outside force to do it and there's it
I'm going on I try the bug source
raising it general that brings a couple
things to my mind Jubilee I I mean what
if you just got 10,000 people that were
incarcerated to put their $10 each in
and come up with this gun you know
they're the ones that have been
supporting themselves to start
foundation that thang could that's
pretty powerful also I wanted to say I
personally feel that money and the lack
of money is almost the bottom-line issue
and I don't mean it like everybody
commits a crime because the money but I
mean like pop communities that have a
lot of poverty they have to if people
are in work they have to be at work
they're usually really low wage jobs
they have to be at work maybe both the
parents if there's only one parent that
parent has to be at work so in my mind I
feel like needing less money instead of
more money is really key like if we
could find a way to reduce the need for
money to constantly be inflated and
people always need more more to pay
their rent or whatever it just seems
like then where people can have an
opportunity to participate in their
community because what happens is they
can't participate in train to help
people in their community because
they're strapped they don't have
a moment to they're stressed out their
kids are stressed out it's hard to be me
or in a world that says money like five
dollars it's nothing anymore twenty
dollars is nothing in fifty bucks that's
nothing a hundred dollars nothing that's
like oh my gosh anything sorry I know I
have to the idea there being a pool of
money but the prisoners themselves have
like they've chosen to put it in there
but also because there's the idea that
you don't want to pay prisoners well
while they're in prison because if it's
a better employment in prison you go to
prison
it's a ridiculous assumption but
whatever it's an assumption that instead
of saying well we have to pay these
people only a dollar an hour to fight
fires
there could be a way to get the best
aware it's like they get to choose
whether they're there and the money
isn't saved by the prison and paint it
you don't I mean like some horrific
capitalist prison system but is instead
paid to a funds that they can then
decide when they get out are we gonna
loan it to chip the prisoners right are
they gonna pay it back is it going to be
like a micro plan this is gonna be that
it's like right you're paying it maybe
not minimum wage but five ten dollars an
hour
and this is that would be again top-down
be like convincing the prison system do
that but if they came from the bottom up
10,000 prisoners coming together and
same we're putting on $10 in for
deciding this they didn't have a
powerful force to lobby with and say
right we have another solution it's not
paying them a dollar an hour and it's
not giving them the money directly that
is they get a tiny bit and the pool gets
it and we have the month which has its
own corruption and hierarchy everything
else but I have to go but are we gonna
maybe we could continue this an athlete
maybe try to do something well we do
this solution racing is the thing we're
working on how do you actually get
10,000 people together and and $100,000
to do that I don't know what next week's
topic is this one was on the books for a
while cuz Brent said that I couldn't do
it top down so it was like challenge
accepted let's see what we could come up
with for prison systems something that
you can't tackle from the bottom up like
come up with something we at the end
Joshua we share what do you think is the
most powerful thing they came up with
what do you think if we could put in
place tomorrow would be the thing you
would most like to see happen
I don't know that's that's fair enough
thanks for coming and hanging out with
us for an hour is this great talent
thank you thank you and you take this
that if we if we ever come up with
something that seems really good and
actionable and like it would be great
like why don't we just do it part of it
is we don't have 10,000 people right so
it's not what do we do with poor people
yeah we could or we could find a find a
our unit anything that would give a
grant and let us market come along to
the process raising conversations I
don't think we need to add more people
to the process racing at the moment once
once we figure out how to invite more
people and how to add more people then
yes anyone and everyone is invited but
like I wanna figure out what the hell
we're doing first before we start asking
for on a third week but don't figure the
note but I love it yeah okay thank you
oh man are you part of the solution
raising facebook group no I'm not it's
it's not one of the game beat ones it's
just solution or anything I'd post what
we're doing all probably if more than
two process racing that that group home
once we figure it out um yeah Shiloh and
Eric what were your most powerful things
they came up with meeting right now
it was nice thank you what are your most
powerful things you think could be in
place right now well not right now we
would take time to code them but you
know now it's super tough question to
pick one cuz I kind of like the idea of
all of them being a part of the solution
about you Eric yeah I mean something
around the idea of restorative justice
where as I said right at the start you
know taking the whole word justice and
criminal out of the equation you know
what I mean and recharacterizing it as a
you know there's nothing wrong with
getting into planet and by conflict I
mean things like you know stealing from
people as well right that's a form of
conflict isn't it you've deprived them
of something they're pissed off about it
right now you're in conflict with each
other so you know their prize up and
down
up and down the scale and the more you
can knit stuff in the bud you know what
I mean deal with it early the less it
becomes big stuff that needs to be dealt
with further down the road so yeah I'm
I'm all-in on there and I just want to
push back on a common wish I think might
have been both of you actually saying
like the choice between restorative
justice and punitive justice and I I
disagree because if somebody wants to go
down the road of units of justice
they'll the next question is well what
is it you want you know what I mean I
mean assuming that they are found guilty
what punishment is it you want answer
and you know that conversation is part
of the restorative justice system they
sort of say the punishment can't be a
part of that process right if this is
what emerges from the process is this
Merson stuff as a punishment and this
person gets to say yes good I feel
better now well so be it right I mean
that remains an option so yeah I either
the restorative justice is a big
umbrella and if punishment is a part of
the arrangement then as I say that that
is that is scope don't I mentioned for
that in particular I don't um I don't
agree with what I was saying
Nessus like I don't and I think that the
victims the victims using the whether
it's punishment or restorative there's a
lot of issues with that because then if
I steal from someone who's into
restorative justice I get less of a
punishment than if I steal for someone
who's not it's like the victims the same
you got something stolen but like the
person who stole depending on who you
stole from they get to choose which path
does your whole life right we see it all
the time and it wouldn't someone's like
I mean friends with my with the person I
was victimized and that's a beautiful
story but it's not the common place and
so that person gets less of a punishment
for everyone else gets more right it's
based on who they kind of chose luckily
is their victim but necessarily right I
mean you know you take the example of
someone steal someone's wallet right
someone leaves their wallet lying on a
table and someone steals is they're not
assaulted them right they just pinched
their wallet and it's a cheap nasty
plastic wallet and they say there's no
money in it and they just throw it away
right in the wallets gone now you know
in now in a punitive judge you if you to
go to court for that
they would be there probably probation
maybe something like that right whereas
in the restorative justice
situation once you actually get into the
case you find that in that cheap plastic
wallet was a photograph of the girl's
brother who died three years ago and so
the thing can't be replaced right and so
she's traumatized and grieving over the
loss of this they even though it has no
monetary value whatsoever and now the
retribution is the wrong word the
balancing the the rebalancing shall we
say of this situation may involves very
very much more than the simple probation
they would have got in the pew statistic
so this is what I mean I think
restorative justice can can can make the
context of the thing front and center
you know the the actuality of the actual
thing that actually happened to the
actual people you know that makes that
the the the thing right and if everyone
went through a story of justice I would
agree but the issue is that that person
who lost their brothers pitt photo right
or loved ones photo could be the person
who's like it's only a photo my brother
would have wanted me to do the
restorative part and chosen that one and
the one who lost well I had to get a
noob license you understand a convenient
memory it's not necessarily about the
impact
oh that's restorative justice it's about
my how much I feel I was impacted and
it's not necessarily the truth because I
think that's my point is so that if
everyone's restorative justice then okay
that's the path but if the victim
chooses whether restorative or this then
it comes up with all of the will then
the person committing the crime is its
luck whether the person you perpetrated
on is gonna choose punitive or sorta
it's just the point that I was trying to
make but I don't think I actually got to
we are past the hour though I would like
to say that the my most powerful thing I
think we could do the ten thousand
people hundred thousand is to ask people
who committed crimes how the
conversation about what would have got
like what would have been in place to
not because it's powerful information
and I would love to see that happen but
I also think one of the most powerful
things 10,000 evil could do together to
help the criminal justice system in
general is start tracking judges and
police officers for their racist or lack
thereof and and be able to see more
easily when someone gets shot well look
at their long history of you're right
this was an isolated event or not
because that also like when
a black person experiences something in
the world it's gonna appear to them that
it's racist and the question is with the
person perpetrating it do it to a person
who's not black or not and you don't
know that without the data you don't
know that based on the black person's
experience right well the cop said X
they're racist no did they say that to
all of the like did they also say that
to way like it takes data to actually
see it and I don't even think the cop
would know right they would need to see
their own data and say oh my god you're
right I do pourable I pull over black
people more than I love white people
with that right like and then I give
them tickets more often I didn't even
know right like it doesn't necessarily
mean it's nefarious in fact it's almost
more dangerous when it's not because you
don't know it is but anyway I'm getting
so I'm sure I can serve you know my
conversation that I think tracking the
data so that that information is there
as well as having conversations of
people who've been in it and having them
generate the solutions
howdy not because the reason I don't
want to move forward with doing this is
there's only four of us having this
conversation
there aren't 10,000 of us having
thousands of us or just the option for
thousands of people to have the
conversation and then listing those
conversations and picking the most
powerful best solution and moving
forward together as 10,000 with that is
I think a very powerful once we figure
even a tiny bit of that out everything
happens rapidly Charlie what do you
think is the most powerful umm I love
this idea of tracking as well I think
that would be very helpful but I think
it would be pretty helpful as well if we
required people except for maybe murder
and read or I don't know even that I
think anyone that commits a crime maybe
they have to start with restorative
justice with their first three crimes
and hopefully there isn't a fourth one
or whatever and then they start to go
into the punitive system at least that
would give an opportunity for because I
like the idea and just straight-up
restorative justice and from the
beginning and I love the idea of making
like I think what we lack in society is
making those connections and so as Eric
was saying once you start to have that
human and interaction with someone and
start to see their what you've done
it's drastically different than just
knowing you've done a crime and then
trying to either hide it or ignore it or
whatever or distance yourself from it it
makes it's just a huge difference - Eric
did you share yours he said he said you
kind of not really very clear but
something is something around that
notion you know as I was saying before
and this comes back to what both of you
are also saying earlier on it's
something like I remember reading a
stack a while ago and it may not be
quite right but it's something like 90%
of all crimes are either crimes of
acquisition or are drug related you know
crimes of acquisition the thefts
robberies fraud you know I mean you're
trying to get something off someone else
it's so 90% or more are crimes of
acquisition and drug relation which
means that less than 10% are violent
crimes murders rapes in fact a lot of
violent crimes are associated with
stealing from people right armed
robberies muggings that kind of thing a
lot of that is sort of just aggravated
kinds of acquisition and so you know
with what you were saying if you can
change the landscape where people no
longer are desperate enough to commit
crimes in order to get stuff that they
need and I listen I get it's not always
that sometimes it is just greed as well
but nevertheless greed is incentivized
right having more stuff to get all
Staters this is all incentivizing the
society so none of this really has you
all said earlier on goes away without
everything else also changing at the
same time and I think yeah we try to
instead that helping people not have
that need for more and more money is the
solution so it's like figuring out food
finger no clothing figuring out shelter
and energy and education without needing
to put out more money helps with the
prison system right like it actually
bigger away than tackling the prison
system yeah the prison system is a bad
now and we need to tackle it so like
having different people working on all
of these different fronts everything you
come about and there's new things as
we'll talk about yeah all right we're
gonna post